Did you ever wonder if certain foods
have a direct effect on your health?
Well, I’m here to
solve that mystery
since you are
the foods you eat.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the role diet plays
in preventing and treating mood disorders.
Depression affects more than
150 million people worldwide,
making it a leading cause of
losing healthy years of life
as a result of disability.
Why is depression so common?
Well, it is said “Nothing in
biology makes sense except
in the light of evolution,”
but why would be
evolve to get depressed?
Depression poses a baffling
evolutionary puzzle.
It has such negative effects, but
remains so common and heritable,
meaning a big chunk of risk is
passed down through our genes,
so there must be some
kind of adaptive benefit.
Otherwise, presumably, it would have
been naturally selected against.
Maybe, depression is an evolutionary
strategy for defense against infection.
Infection has been the
leading cause of mortality
throughout human history.
The average life
expectancy was 25,
and it was not uncommon
for half our kids to die.
With such stark capabilities,
infection has been a critical
and potent driving force
in natural selection.
When we become infected, there
is a surge of inflammation
as our body mounts a counterattack,
and then what happens?
We feel lousy. We feel sick,
we get weak, tired, slow, and sleepy.
We don’t see anyone;
we don’t want to do anything;
all we want to do is sleep.
It’s like we’re depressed—
and that’s great for
fighting infection.
Not only does that help us
conserve energy so we can
put up a good fight,
but reduces social contact,
we’re not running around
infecting everyone.
It’s the same reason we evolved
to think poop doesn’t smell good,
or decaying flesh.
That keeps us safe
from infection.
In fact, we see this phenomenon
with other social animals
like honeybees
and mole rats
who feel impelled to crawl off
and die alone when they get sick,
which reduces the risk
to the rest of the community.
The relationship between mental
health and inflammation
was first noted in 1887,
for which the only psychiatrist
to ever win the award
got a Nobel Prize.
But what evidence have we
accumulated in the century since
that inflammation
causes depression?
Well, people who are depressed
have raised inflammatory markers
such as C-reactive protein.
Inflammatory illnesses are associated
with greater rates of major depression.
Indeed, that’s what’s found in
a variety of inflammatory conditions
including more benign
inflammatory conditions,
like as asthma
and allergies,
and that’s important,
suggesting the mood symptoms
are not simply ‘feeling bad
about having a terrible disease’
but may be directly tied
to the inflammation.
Most powerfully, you can
actually induce depression
by inducing inflammation,
like when we give interferon
for certain cancers or
chronic infections—
up to 50% go on to suffer
major depression.
Even just giving a vaccine
can cause enough inflammation
to trigger
depressive symptoms.
Taken together, these studies
are strongly suggestive of
inflammation being a causative
factor of mood symptoms.
So can an anti-inflammatory diet
help prevent depression?
We didn’t know…
until about 43,000 women without
depression were followed,
along with their diets,
for about a dozen years
to see who became depressed,
and it was those who at a more
inflammatory dietary pattern,
characterized by more soda,
refined grains and meat,
suggesting that chronic inflammation
may underlie the association
between diet
and depression.
Normally, we think of omega-3’s
as anti-inflammatory,
but they found fish to
be pro-inflammatory,
associated with increased C-reactive protein
levels consistent with recent findings
that omega-3’s don’t seem to help
with either depression or inflammation.
The most anti-inflammatory
diet is plant-based,
which can cut C-Reactive Protein
levels by 30% within two weeks.
Perhaps because of the anti-
inflammatory properties of antioxidants.
I’ve talked about this before,
but never explained WHY
antioxidants are
anti-inflammatory.
Oxidative damage caused by
free radicals may cause
an autoimmune response in the body
by changing the chemical structures
of otherwise ubiquitous molecules
to generate new structures
that the body
attacks as foreign.
For example, when LDL
cholesterol gets oxidized,
our body creates antibodies
against it and attacks it.
And so clinical depression can be
accompanied by increased oxidative stress
and the autoimmune inflammatory
responses it creates.
Free radicals lead to
auto-immune inflammation.
Where else does inflammation
come from in our diet?
Endotoxins. It’s worth reviewing how
the endotoxins in animal products
can cause a burst of inflammation
within hours of consumption.
What does it
do to our mood?
If you inject endotoxin into people,
within a few hours, inflammation shoots up,
and so does feelings
of depression,
as well as feelings of social
disconnection from people.
Although previous research has
demonstrated that inflammatory activity
contributes to
depressive symptoms,
no work in humans has examined
the effect of experimentally induced
inflammation
on anhedonia—
the lack of reaction to
pleasurable stimuli—
this is an an important
symptom of depression.
No work has been done
that is....
until now.
Within hours of endotoxin
hitting their bloodstream,
these experimental subjects not only
started to feel depressed,
but they had significant
reductions in activity
in the reward center
of the brain.
They were less excited
about winning money
playing video games,
for example in the study.
But by eliminating animal products,
and eating antioxidant rich diets,
we may be able to
prevent or treat depression.
In our next story,
we look at how the natural enzyme
inhibitors in fruits and vegetables
may help explain the
improvement in mood
associated with switching
to a more plant-based diet.
Why does frequent
consumption of vegetables
appear to cut ones odds of
depression by more than half?
And by more frequent they
mean eating vegetables
not 3 or more times a day,
but just 3 or more times a week.
But even that seemed to cut
the odds of developing depression
by 60% after controlling for
a long list of variables.
In the 2012 study that found
that eliminating animal products
improved mood within 2 weeks,
the researchers blamed
arachidonic acid,
primarily in chicken and eggs,
which may adversely
impact mental health
via a cascade of
brain inflammation.
But better moods on
plant-based diets
could also be from
the good stuff in plants,
a class of phytonutrients
that crosses the blood
brain barrier into our heads.
This recent review in the
journal Nutritional Neuroscience,
suggests that eating lots
of fruits and vegetables
"may present a noninvasive
natural and inexpensive"
"therapeutic means to
support a healthy brain."
Yeah, but how?
Well, to understand the latest,
we need to understand
the underlying biology,
the so-called monoamine
theory of depression -
the thought that
depression may arise
out of a chemical
imbalance in the brain.
Here's the oversimplified version:
One of the ways that billions
of nerves in our brain
communicate with one another
is through chemical signals
called neurotransmitters.
Note the two nerve cells
don't actually touch—
there's a physical
gap between them.
To bridge that gap,
when one nerve wants
to tap the other
on the shoulder
it releases chemicals
into that gap,
including three monoamines:
serotonin, dopamine,
and norepinephrine.
These neurotransmitters
then float over
to the other nerve
to get its attention.
The first nerve then
sucks them back up
to be reused the next
time it wants to talk,
but it's also constantly
manufacturing more,
and an enzyme, monoamine oxidase,
is constantly chewing them up
to maintain just the right amount.
The way cocaine appears to work
is by acting as a monoamine
re-uptake inhibitor.
It blocks the first nerve
from sucking back up
those three chemicals and so
there's this constant
tapping on the shoulder,
this constant signaling
to the next nerve.
Amphetamines work
in the same way,
but also increase
monoamine release.
Ecstacy works like speed,
but just causes comparatively
more serotonin release.
After awhile, the next nerve
may be like "enough already!"
and down-regulate its receptors
to turn down the volume.
It puts in ear plugs.
So you need more and more
of the drug to get
the same effect.
Then when you are
not on the drug
you may feel crappy because
normal volume transmission
just isn't getting
through as much.
Antidepressants are thought
to work along similar mechanisms.
People who are depressed
appear to have
elevated levels of monoamine
oxidase in their brain.
That's the enzyme that breaks
down those neurotransmitters.
If the levels of your neurotransmitter-
eating enzyme is elevated,
then your levels of
neurotransmitters drops,
and you become depressed,
or so the theory goes.
So a number of different classes
of drugs have been developed.
The tricyclic antidepressants,
named because they have
three rings like a tricycle,
appear to block norepinephrine
and dopamine re-uptake,
and so even though your enzymes
may be eating these up
at an accelerated rate,
what gets released
sticks around longer.
Then there came the
SSRIs like Prozac,
the selective serotonin
re-uptake inhibitors.
Now you can know
what that means—
they just blocks the
re-uptake of serotonin.
Then there are drugs
that just block
the re-uptake of
norepinephrine,
or more dopamine
or the opposite.
But if the problem is too much
high levels of monoamine oxidase,
why not just
block the enzyme?
Make a monoamine oxidase inhibitor—
and of course they did,
but they're considered
drugs of last resort
because of serious side effects,
not the least of which is
the dreaded "cheese effect,"
where eating certain
foods like certain cheeses
while on the drug can have
potentially fatal consequences.
If only there was a way
to tamp down the activity
of this enzyme without the whole
bleed-into-your-brain-thing
and die-thing.
Now we can finally talk
about the latest theory
as to why fruits and vegetables
may improve our mood.
There are inhibitors of that depression-
associated enzyme in various plants.
There are phytonutrients in spices,
such as cloves, oregano,
cinnamon, nutmeg,
but people don't eat enough spices
to get enough into the brain.
This dark green leafy has a lot,
but its name is tobacco,
which may actually
be one of the reasons
cigarettes make smokers
feel so good.
OK, but what if you don't want
brain bleeds or lung cancer?
Well, there is a phytonutrient found
in apples, berries, and grapes,
and kale, onions, and green tea
that may indeed affect our brain
biology enough to improve our mood.
Finally today,
the results of an interventional
trial of diet and mood.
A 2014 systematic review and
meta-analysis of dietary patterns
and depression concluded that a healthy
diet pattern was significantly associated
with the reduced odds of depression.
But out of the 21 studies they could
find in the medical literature,
they were only able to find one
randomized controlled trial,
considered the study design that
provides the highest level of evidence.
And it was the study I profiled in
"Improving Mood Through Diet",
in which removing meat,
fish, poultry and eggs
improved several mood
scores in just two weeks.
We've known those eating plant-based
tend to have healthier mood states”
less tension, anxiety, depression,
anger, hostility and fatigue,
but you couldn't tell if
it was cause and effect
until you put it to the test,
which they finally did.
But what could account
for such rapid results?
Well, eating vegetarian does give
you a better antioxidant status,
which may help with depression.
Also, as I've previously addressed,
how consumption of even a
single carbohydrate-rich meal
can improve depression, tension, anger,
confusion, sadness, fatigue, alertness,
and calmness scores among patients
with PMS, but what about long term?
Overweight men and women were
randomized into a low carb, high fat diet
or high carb, low fat diet for a year.
By the end of the year, who had less
depression, anxiety, anger and hostility,
feelings of dejection,
tension, fatigue, better
vigor, less confusion
or mood disturbances?
These sustained improvements
in mood in the low fat group
compared with the low carb group
are consistent with results
from epidemiological studies
showing that diets high in carbohydrate
and low in fat and protein
are associated with lower
levels of anxiety and depression
and have beneficial effects
on psychological well-being.
The overall amount of fat in their diet
didn't change in this study, though.
But the type of fat did.
Their arachidonic acid
intake fell to zero.
Arachidonic acid is an
inflammatory omega-6 fatty acid
that can adversely impact mental health
via a cascade of neuroinflammation.
It may inflame our brain.
High blood levels in the bloodstream
have been associated
with a greater likelihood
of suicide risk, for example,
and major depressive episodes.
How can we stay
away from the stuff?
Well, Americans are exposed
to arachidonic acid
primarily through
chicken and eggs.
But when you remove chicken
and eggs, and other meat,
we can eliminate preformed
arachidonic acid from our diet.
So while high-quality treatment studies
investigating the impact of diet
on depression are scarce, there
is that successful 2-week trial,
but even better:
How about 22 weeks?
Overweight or diabetic employees
of a major insurance corporation
received either weekly group instruction
on a whole food plant-based diet
or no diet instruction
for five and a half months.
There was no portion size restriction,
no calorie counting, no carb counting.
No change in exercise.
No meals were provided, but the
company cafeteria did start offering
daily options such as lentil soup,
minestrone, bean burritos.
No meat, eggs, dairy, oil or junk, yet
they reported greater diet satisfaction
compared with the control group
participants who had no diet restrictions.
How'd they do though?
More participants in the
plant-based intervention group
reported improved digestion, increased
energy, better sleep than usual
at week 22 compared
with the control group.
They also reported a significant
increase in physical functioning,
general health, vitality,
and mental health.
There was also significant
improvements in work productivity,
thought to be due in large part
to their improvements in health.
So what this study demonstrated was
that a cholesterol-free diet is acceptable,
not only in research settings, but
in a typical corporate environment,
improving quality of life
and productivity at little cost.
All we need now is a large,
randomized trial for confirmation,
but we didn't have
such a thing, until now.
Ten corporate sites across the country
from San Diego to Macon, Georgia.
Same kind of set up as before.
Can a plant-based nutrition program
in a multi-center, corporate setting
improve depression, anxiety,
and productivity?
Yes. Significant improvements
in depression, anxiety, fatigue,
emotional well being,
and daily functioning.
Lifestyle interventions have
an increasingly apparent role
in physical and mental health,
and among the most effective
of these is the use
of plant-based diets.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.